Hey, friends. Dave here with Transfer
Express, and today we're talking artwork
requirements and print standards as it
relates to screen printed and
direct-to-film heat transfers. We're
going to explain what these minimum
requirements are, how they differ
between transfer types, and how you
could check your artwork to identify any
issues before they arise, ensuring
headache-free, quality prints every
time. To top it off, we'll print below
and above print minimums to help
illustrate what [music] these results
look like on your finished t-shirts. So,
are you ready? Let's get to it. If you
are new to Transfer Express, we are the
world's largest supplier of custom
screen printed and digital heat
transfers, heat presses, free
customizable designs, wholesale apparel,
and expert advice to help grow your
[music] t-shirt business. If you haven't
already, subscribe. We're kicking out
new videos like this one every single
week. So, to kick us off here, let's
define what we're talking about with
minimum artwork requirements or print
standards. Essentially, we are talking
about the minimum line weight or text
size in your artwork file that you could
print on your apparel. So, the finished
print matches how you see it on screen.
This is also going to account for our
show-through areas or negative space.
So, these areas don't disappear
completely in those final prints.
[music]
We are working with liquid-based ink
with our screen prints after all. Now,
general industry minimums for screen
printing are 1 point for line thickness,
and then this applies to font sizing,
too, with the stem or line of each
character no thinner than 1 point. So,
[music] that's right around 16 points
with most fonts when you're printing on
[music] fabric. Now, here at Transfer
Express, we have a very handy tool that
you could use in our Easy View online
designer to check both your line weight
and show-through areas for our different
transfer types. We made a whole video on
using that tool. We'll link it right
here and down in the description below.
Now, with that tool, you notice there's
a couple transfer types listed on it,
and we're going to be covering the most
popular here today. The
printed transfers and UltraColor Max
direct-to-film transfers. For our
examples, we're going to be using a
simple testing chart for both screen
printing and direct-to-film with areas
on our transfers here printing above and
below the minimum requirements. We have
our show-through areas for screen
printing at the top, some line weights
from 0.5 point to 15 point, and text
[music] two ways. One as positive ink,
and then knocked out as negative space
to the garment color. On the side, we
have just a stylized half-tone drawdown
starting at 2 points for the dot size,
just for some detail reference.
[snorts]
Now, for our Goof-Proof screen printed
transfers, let's start with the minimum
line weight, and that's going to put us
right at 1 point or 0.012
inches, the screen printing industry
standard. Now, you can see here for our
0.5 point line, it looks pretty good
printed, and it did [music] in fact
print. However, we may run into some
durability issues where it's not going
to meet that standard of 50-plus
wash-dry cycles that we have all of our
transfers independently [music] tested
for. Like I mentioned earlier, you'll
want to ensure whatever font you use
meets those standards, too, [music] in
terms of thickness of each line on the
characters. Here on our example, we have
printed
um eight or 9 point font is right where
we're clean and clear using a standard
Arial typeface. [music]
Now, any smaller and we're going to run
into issues like you see here on our
prints. The actual size of your text
will differ depending on the specific
font you [music] use as some are thicker
or thinner [snorts] than others. It's
just something important to keep in mind
when you're using small text on, say,
inside tag [music] prints. Now, this is
a great opportunity to stop and mention
the minimum show-through thickness at
2.8 [music] points or 0.04 inches. With
small text, you're going to notice this
the most with letters like P or O here
closing up into solid areas of ink. And
as knocked-out text, we lose a lot of
the text, pretty much all the way to uh
man, 18 point font is really the
smallest I feel safe [music] going where
we could actually read the words. You
might even want to go larger. For our
minimum show-through line weight up here
at the top of our graphic, you'll notice
that we really can't see the break in
the solid area at 1.5 point, which is
underneath the minimum. Here on our
white version, you actually can barely
see it still here, but it almost closed
up. Now, with increased pressure on
press, if you don't have a Hotronix
press with that exact [music] number, it
may cause the inks to spread a little
bit more when you're on your heat press,
and that's going to cause it to
completely fill in. And that's why
there's a clear set standard of 2.8
[music] points where it's never going to
fill in. You can see nice and clear here
on both of our examples. Now, take this
into consideration when you're setting
up your artwork for printing and what is
critical to print clean and clear.
You're going to want to ensure that text
is readable, of course, but say for some
fine detail, it might not be
mission-critical to have it clean and
clear in your print. So, for example, it
may be okay if you miss a few seeds in a
strawberry with them filling in on your
final print. It's all going to depend on
your specific artwork. [music] Now,
let's shift on over to direct-to-film
transfers. Now, before we dive into
specifics, there's a few differences I'd
like to point out. The first being the
show-through areas. Since the printing
process is different for direct-to-film,
the inks do not spread like our
plastisol screen printing inks do under
the pressure of the heat press like we
saw. So, it's a little bit more like
heat transfer vinyl where it's just
going straight down. Now, this allows us
to achieve finer show-through areas that
we can't achieve with those screen
printed plastisol inks that we just
looked at.
[music]
Now, this also allows us to get much
better definition in small characters,
for example, here in our knocked-out
text. [music] However, our minimum line
weight is actually slightly larger than
what could be achieved with screen
printing. So, instead of 1 point, our
minimum with DTF transfers is 1.29
[music]
points. So, here, while our finished
print looks okay, we're actually going
to have some breakup when we just start
rubbing it with our finger here, and
we're going to have wash durability
issues under those minimum artwork
requirements.
[music]
Since direct-to-film is a different
printing process, the adhesive needs ink
to hold on to, along with a white
backing [music] to ensure colors are
fully opaque on light or dark garments.
So, it's easy to see when you take a
look at the backside of the transfer.
You can see these areas like the fine
lines and small text on our black ink
transfer here aren't thick enough to
have white printed behind them, and that
means they're probably not going to have
an adequate amount of adhesive on them.
Now, luckily at Transfer Express, we
take all of the guesswork out of these
minimums when printing direct-to-film
with an industry-exclusive live proof in
our review step. As the final step
before ordering, our system is going to
analyze your artwork and identify
printing issues like these before you
order. So, you can make corrections or
approve your art before placing your
order. As you can see in our example,
this step in the Easy View online
designer identified pretty much all of
the areas that we're concerned about
here on the actual transfer that we
received. Now, these areas are going to
print to the garment just like we saw,
but without that proper amount of
adhesive, they break down with just
rubbing, and they're definitely going to
wear prematurely and have durability
issues when you start to launder them.
So, it's best to meet the minimums of
those print [music] standards. Now,
again, just like with DTF, and just like
with our screen printed transfers, some
little fine details you may [music] be
okay with when you see it in that review
step. So, if it's just a little corner
here or there, most likely it's going to
be completely fine to print with your
artwork. Now, if it's text or important
elements that are being flagged in that
review step, then it might be time to
modify your artwork. But regardless of
the product type you're ordering, we are
here to help with a team of artists
standing by ready to modify your art.
Now, artwork help is free with screen
printed transfers like the first example
that we looked at with our Goof-Proof
screen printed transfers, Hot Split, and
ElastaPrint transfers. Now, our
UltraColor Max direct-to-film transfers,
there is a $26 charge for any additional
file help. So, you can see here we did
push the limits of what we could do with
screen printed and direct-to-film heat
transfers, all in the spirit of helping
decorators just like you. Now, do you
have a topic you'd like to see us cover
or questions about anything we covered
here today? Let us know down in the
comments section below. I'll answer them
personally, and I always love to keep
the conversation going. As always, be
sure to hit that like button and
subscribe to the Transfer Express
YouTube page right here, and stay
up-to-date on all of the helpful t-shirt
printing tips, tricks, [music]
inspiration, and education that we're
dropping every single week. But until
next time, I'm Dave.
Happy pressing.